[Ziji Palace]
[자극전]
Empress Dowager,
태후마마
you must seek justice for us.
부디 소신을 위해 힘써주십시오
Why are you crying?
왜 그러느냐
Xiao Wuyi is back.
소무의가 돌아왔습니다
Didn't he die in battle at Jiuzhang Plain?
그 자는 구장원에서 전사한 게 아니었더냐?
The news is fake.
전부 거짓 정보입니다
He is perfectly alive.
그자는 멀쩡히 살아있습니다
This morning, he even led troops to my Lantai gathering.
심지어 오전에는 군사를 이끌고 제 난대회에 나타났습니다
Adjutant Chen and Vice Minister Wei
진 참군과 위 소부가
just refused to write poems praising his achievements,
그자의 공덕을 칭송하는 시를 짓지 않겠다고 하자
and he had them killed on the spot.
그자의 손에 죽임을 당했습니다
Xiao Wuyi brought troops into the capital without an edict
소무의가 조서도 없이 군사를 이끌고 경성으로 와
and wrongfully killed court officials.
무고한 조정 대신을 죽였으니
This is treason!
이는 역모입니다
Did he bring his army back too?
대군도 이끌고 돌아왔느냐?
Not quite.
그건 아닙니다
It's fine if he didn't bring the army back.
대군을 데려오지 않았다면 별일 아닐 것이다
After all, Xiao Wuyi's wife, the Crown Princess,
어찌됐든 소무의의 세자빈은
is my niece.
내 조카딸이니
I'm sure that Lord Xiao and his son remain loyal to His Majesty.
소씨 부자는 폐하께 끝까지 충성을 다할 것이다
Aunt,
숙모님
can a mere marriage prove loyalty?
세자빈 하나로 어찌 충심을 논한단 말입니까
Xiao Wuyi can kill officials at will now,
소무의는 지금 멋대로 대신을 죽이고
with no regard for the law.
국법을 무시하는 등
His wild ambitions are obvious.
그 흉악한 속내를 드러내고 있습니다
Now that His Majesty is unwell,
지금 황형께서 옥체가 미령하시어
the court is unstable and people are panicking.
조정도 불안정하고 인심이 흉흉합니다
If at this time,
만약 이때
Xiao Wuyi commands his troops and declares himself ruler,
소무의가 군사를 일으켜 자립하면
you and His Majesty will be sitting ducks.
숙모님과 황형의 자리도 위태롭습니다
Then in your opinion,
그럼 너는
what should we do?
어찌하면 좋겠느냐
Give me the imperial guards so we can prepare early.
금군을 신에게 맡겨 대비하게 해 주십시오
Let's strike first
저희가 미리 선수를 쳐서
and get rid of Xiao Wuyi.
소무의를...
Aunt, there is no time to hesitate.
숙모님, 더는 망설일 시간이 없습니다
We are family after all.
저희는 한가족이지 않습니까
Empress Dowager!
태후마마
His Majesty has coughed up blood and fainted again.
폐하께서 각혈하시고 혼절하셨습니다
My son!
아들아...
Summon the royal physician!
태의를 불러라, 태의를
This old fox
저 늙은 여우가
refuses to name me Crown Prince
날 태자로 책봉하려 하지도 않고
and won't even give me military authority.
군사권도 주지 않는군
She's only ever used me as a shield.
날 방패막이로 쓰려는 것이겠지
So you all want to use me as a pawn?
다들 날 그저 장기말로 쓰려하다니
Then don't blame me for flipping the board.
내가 판을 없어도 내 탓은 하지 말아라
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[작골]
[Episode 2]
[제2화]
The Crown Princess doesn't like to go out.
세자빈은 평소에 외출을 즐기지 않고
She likes to read.
책 읽기를 좋아한다
Her favorite is Mencius,
맹자를 가장 좋아하지
she doesn't like Laozi and Zhuangzi,
노장 사상은 싫어하고
and she is quite familiar with Buddhist scriptures.
불경에도 조예가 깊어
If you want to know more about her,
그 애를 알고 싶으면
you can start with the books she likes.
그 아이가 좋아하는 책부터 시작해 보아라
You haven't been back
세자빈이 말은 안 했지만
for these years.
네가 몇 년이나
The Crown Princess doesn't say it,
돌아오지 않아서
but she misses you very much.
속으로는 널 무척 그리워했다
She's always in Jinyi Courtyard
늘 근익원에서 기도하며
praying for your safety on the battlefield.
네가 전장에서 무사히 돌아오길 바랐지
Although Ziqi
게다가 자기는
is Madam Rui's son,
비록 예씨 부인의 소생이긴 하지만
the Crown Princess has always taken good care of him
세자빈이 줄곧 정성으로 돌보고
and taught him carefully.
마음 써서 가르쳤어
You should thank her properly.
고맙다고 해야 할 거야
Your Highness, I found out.
세자 전하, 알아냈습니다
The stalls of the Young Master of Miraculous Craft at the Lantai gathering
난대회에 있던 묘수 공자의 좌판은
were all set up by the Grand Tutor's Mansion.
모두 태부부 사람들이 차린 것이었습니다
Grand Tutor Xie?
사 태부가?
That lady is Grand Tutor Xie's daughter.
그 낭자는 사 태부의 딸이겠군
If Grand Tutor Xie only has one daughter,
사 태부에게 딸이 하나뿐이라면
then it's her.
그 아가씨가 맞을 겁니다
There is a rumor in the capital
경성 내에 소문이 자자합니다
that Prince Changsha is about to marry the Grand Tutor's daughter.
장사왕이 태부의 딸을 아내로 맞기 위해서
The betrothal gifts have been sent to the Grand Tutor's Mansion.
예물까지 태부부로 보냈다고 말입니다
Does the Grand Tutor also support Prince Changsha?
설마 태부께서도 장사왕을 지지하시는 걸까요?
I am looking forward to this wedding more and more.
이 혼례가 점점 더 기대되는군
Wuyi, I am talking about the Crown Princess!
둘째야, 지금 내가 세자빈 얘기를 하고 있잖냐
Since you know the Crown Princess so well,
형님이 세자빈을 그리 잘 아신다면
why didn't you marry her yourself back then?
직접 혼인하시지 그러셨습니까?
You!
너
Crown Princess.
세자빈
Greetings, Your Highness.
세자 전하를 뵙습니다
So you are the Crown Princess?
그대가 세자빈이오?
Yes, I am.
그렇습니다
Nice to meet you.
처음 뵙겠소
Thank you for your efforts today.
오늘 수고 많았소
The Beifu pretended to be defeated
북부군이 패한 척하며
and lured the enemy into the city,
적을 성 안으로 유인한 뒤
then surrounded them and wiped most of them out.
북진 동로 대군을
The entire Eastern Army of Northern Qin has been wiped out,
전멸시켰으며
and the Five-City territory has been reclaimed.
다섯 성을 수복했고
The remaining enemy forces fled in defeat.
적군은 패하여 달아났습니다
Here is the roster of meritorious soldiers,
공을 세운 장병들의 명단을 올리오니
awaiting Your Majesty's reward.
성은을 내려 주시옵소서
I want to impeach Xiao Wuyi, the Heir of Prince Jing'an.
신, 정안왕 세자 소무의를 탄핵하고자 합니다
At yesterday's Lantai gathering,
어제 난대회에서
Xiao Wuyi blatantly disregarded the laws of the state
소무의가 국법을 무시하고
and murdered Chen Guangtong, the Military Advisor,
병조참군 진광동과
and Wei Qianli, the Household Department Adjutant.
소부부승 위천리를 살해하였습니다
I second that. I second that.
신도 동의하옵니다
Empress Dowager,
태후 폐하께 아뢰옵니다
Chen Guangtong leaked military intelligence,
진광동은 군사 기밀을 누설하고
delayed military operations, and held up provisions.
군사 작전을 지연시키고 군량 보급을 늦췄습니다
Vice Minister Wei, who oversaw military equipment,
또한 위 소부는
passed off inferior goods and embezzled military funds.
군수품을 저급으로 바꿔치기하여 군자금을 횡령했습니다
The two men were guilty of countless crimes.
두 사람은 자신의 죄가 중함을 아록
Unable to face punishment, they took their own lives.
죄가 두려워 자결한 것입니다
Here are years of
이것은 두 사람이
correspondence
수년간 주고받은 서신과
and records of embezzlement.
횡령 장부이옵니다
Please investigate thoroughly, Your Majesties.
폐하와 태후마마께서 명찰하여 주시옵소서
Shameless!
참으로 부끄러움을 모르십니다
Everyone in the court
조정의 모든 사람이
knows you killed Adjutant Chen and Vice Minister Wei yourself
전하가 난대회에서
at the Lantai gathering!
진 참군과 위 소부를 직접 죽인 것을 알고 있습니다
Yesterday's poetry gathering was hosted by Prince Changsha.
어제의 시회는 장사왕 전하께서 직접 주관하셨습니다
Everyone knows
조정 안팎이 모두 알다시피
that Prince Changsha is the future Crown Prince.
장사왕 전하께서는 미래의 군주이십니다
How would I dare commit murder in front of His Highness?
신이 어찌 감히 전하 앞에서 사람 목숨을 쉽게 여기겠습니까
That would only embarrass His Highness.
이는 전하의 체면을 깎는 일이 아닙니까
Your Highness, were these two killed by me
전하, 그 두 사람은 제가 죽인 것입니까
or did they commit suicide out of guilt?
아니면 죄가 두려워 스스로 자결한 것입니까?
They took their own lives out of guilt.
죄가 두려워 자결한 것입니다
Thank you, Your Highness,
신의 누명을 벗겨 주셔서
for clearing my name.
감사드립니다
I naturally believe in Young Lord Xiao.
나는 당연히 세자를 믿는다
Young Lord Xiao has worked hard defending the territory over the years.
요 몇 년간 소 세자가 국토를 지키느라 고생이 많았고
With numerous military achievements,
군공도 혁혁하니
he should be well rewarded and promoted.
후하게 포상해야 마땅하겠지
You...
세자
Thank you for your grace, Your Majesty.
태후 폐하의 은혜에 감사드립니다
I dare not decline the rewards meant for the soldiers.
장병들을 위한 포상은 사양치 않겠습니다
I don't seek promotion for myself;
신은 높은 벼슬과 작위를 바라지 않습니다
I only ask for one person.
허나, 부탁드릴 것이 있습니다
Please grant me permission to marry, Empress Dowager.
태후 폐하 혼인을 윤허하여 주시옵소서
I am willing to marry the daughter of Grand Tutor Xie
소신은 사태부의 여식을
with the rites of a principal consort.
정비의 예로 맞이하고자 합니다
Grand Tutor.
태부
The Empress Dowager is unwell
오늘은 태후 마마께서 옥체가 편찮으시어
and will not see anyone today.
뵙지 못하시겠다 합니다
She has sent you a food box
찬합을 하사하셨으니
and asked you to return early.
태부께서는 이만 돌아가시지요
Eunuch He,
하 내관
please deliver another message to the Empress Dowager for me.
번거롭겠지만 태후 마마께 제 말을 전해 주시오
Grand Tutor,
태부 어른
I cannot take any more messages for you today.
오늘은 말씀을 전해 드릴 수가 없습니다
Is this the Empress Dowager's intention?
이것이 태후 마마의 뜻이오?
The Empress Dowager often says: Enemies surround us on all sides.
태후 마마께서 늑대 떼가 사방에 있다고 말씀하셨습니다
Within the court, there is Prince Changsha;
안으로는 장사왕이 있고
beyond it, there is the Beifu Army.
밖으로는 북부군이 있지요
Young Lord Xiao holds military power
소 세자는 군사권을 쥐고 있고
and his achievements shake the realm.
군공 또한 혁혁합니다
Only the Beifu Army can defend the northern border.
오직 북부군만이 북쪽 국경을 지킬 수 있지요
The Emperor and I sit on the throne helplessly,
폐하께서는 높은 자리에 앉아 계실 뿐
with no way out.
이미 살아날 길이 없다고 하셨습니다
Mind your words, Eunuch.
내관께선 언행을 삼가시오
Grand Tutor,
태부
the Empress Dowager understands a father's love for his child.
태후마마께서도 태부의 부성애를 알고 계십니다
She only hopes the Grand Tutor
부디 태부께서도
might also understand a mother's love for hers.
태후마마의 자애로운 모성애를 헤아려 주십시오
I understand.
알겠소
I
신
accept the imperial edict.
명을 받들겠습니다
Thank you for the grace.
성은이 망극하옵니다
But this jade must be quite valuable.
근데 이 옥, 꽤 비싸지 않아?
Fine jade suits a gentleman.
군자에게는 좋은 옥이 어울려
Mao is the best gentleman in the world.
이무는 세상에서 가장 훌륭한 군자니까
He naturally deserves the best jade.
당연히 가장 좋은 옥을 가져야지
Don't frown.
인상 좀 펴
Didn't Mao say he'd be back soon?
이무가 곧 돌아온다고 했잖아
You should be happy.
기뻐해야지
True.
그렇네
Brother said he had prepared surprises for all of us.
오라버니가 우리 주려고 깜짝 선물도 준비했대
Father,
아버지
Mother.
어머니
I didn't do anything wrong, did I?
제가 뭘 잘못한 건 아니죠?
I really didn't do anything.
저는 아무것도 안 했는데요
I made this myself.
이, 이건 제가 직접 만든 거예요
Lady Xie, receive the imperial decree!
사 씨는 교지를 받으라
I'm really going to hang myself.
이럴 거면 진짜 목맬 거예요
-No, no, no. -Don't try to stop me, anyone.
- 그러지 마세요 - 아무도 막지 마
-My Lady, come down. -I'm going to hang myself.
- 아가씨, 얼른 내려오세요 - 나 목 매요
My Lady, stop making a scene and come down.
아가씨, 장난치지 마세요
Darling, this...
부인, 이건...
Father,
아버지
Xiao Wuyi killed two courtiers
그 소무의라는 자는
in front of so many people
많은 사람들이 보는 앞에서
at the Lantai gathering.
조정 대신을 두 명이나 죽였어요
If I marry him,
제가 그 사람에게 시집을 가면
in a few days,
며칠 안 돼서
you'll have to collect my corpse.
제 시신을 거두셔야 할 거예요
If that's the case,
그럴 바에는
I might as well hang myself right now.
차라리 지금 목매달아 죽겠어요
I'm really not joking.
저 정말 진지해요
I'm hanging myself now!
지금 바로 목맬 거예요
I'm hanging myself.
목맬 거라고요
My Lady!
아가씨
Why not switch to a hemp rope?
차라리 삼베 밧줄로 바꾸지 그러니?
It's sturdier.
더 튼튼한 걸로 말이야
This is your favorite white porcelain teacup,
그건 악군이 네게 선물한
given by Lejun.
네가 가장 아끼는 백자 찻잔
This is the incense burner you made yourself,
그건 네가 사흘이나 걸려 만든
which was fired for three days.
향초고 말이야
This is a treasure box
그 보물 상자는
made of golden-thread nanmu wood.
금사남목으로 만든 거란다
This is nice.
이건 괜찮겠네
The palace has issued the imperial edict.
궁에서 교지가 내려왔다
Do you want to defy it?
설마 교지를 어기기라도 하겠다는 거냐?
Yao Yao,
요요
the Empress Dowager has long known that Prince Changsha
태후께선 장사왕이 너와의 혼인을 원하는 걸 알고 계셨다
wants to marry you, and she knows I have always refused.
이 아비가 줄곧 반대한 것도 아셨지
With Young Lord Xiao stepping in,
그런데 소 세자가 끼어드니
the Empress Dowager agreed to the marriage without hesitation.
태후께서 조금의 망설임도 없이 혼사를 허락하신 거야
Do you know why?
왜인지 아느냐?
The fiercer the fight between Prince Jing'an's Mansion and Prince Changsha gets,
정안왕부와 장사왕이 치열하게 싸울수록
the safer it is for the frail
몸이 약하신 폐하와 태후께서
Emperor and the Empress Dowager.
더 안전해지기 때문이지
When the snipe and the clam grapple,
어부지리라는
the fisherman profits.
말처럼 말이야
Your marriage is nothing
너의 이 혼사는
more than a pawn in the struggle for power.
이번 혼사는 혼란스러운 정국을 뒤흔들기 위한 장기말에 불과해
Then let whoever wants to be that pawn take their place.
그럼 그 장기말은 누가 되든 상관없잖아요
I won't.
전 안 할 거예요
The Empress Dowager's own niece
태후마마의 친조카딸이
has been married into Prince Jing'an's Mansion for years,
정안왕부에 시집간 지 몇 년인데
and Young Lord Xiao doesn't even recognize her.
소 세자께선 얼굴도 모르세요
If I marry into that family,
만약 제가 시집가서
and end up like the Crown Princess,
세자빈처럼 되면요?
then every day I...
그럼 저는 매일...
Isn't that perfect?
그럼 잘된 거 아니니?
You don't like him anyway.
어차피 좋아하지도 않는데
Young Lord Xiao is away on expeditions,
소 세자가 멀리 원정을 떠나면
and you'd be alone in the manor every day.
너는 매일 독수공방할 테고
By then,
그때가 되면
you can build waterwheels if you want,
물레방아를 만들든
or fire white porcelain if you want.
백자를 굽든
No one will control you anymore.
아무도 널 간섭하지 않을 건데
Isn't this the life you've dreamed of?
네가 꿈에 그리던 게 그런 날들 아니니?
Since it's a foregone conclusion,
이미 정해진 일이니
stop letting your imagination run wild.
딴생각하지 마라
Who you marry doesn't make much difference.
누구한테 시집가든 그게 그거야
No, Mother.
아니에요, 어머니
I want to marry Mao.
저는 무한테 시집갈 거라고요
I...
저는...
Father,
아버지
I want to marry Mao.
저는 무한테 시집갈 거예요
-Fine. -I...
- 그래 - 저는...
I understand.
알겠다
No, you don't.
아니요, 아버지
I want to marry Mao.
저는 이무한테 시집갈 거라니까요
I hear that the daughter of Grand Tutor Xie Huaigui,
태부 사회귀의 여식 사씨는
from a distinguished family,
명문가의 규수로 덕망이 뛰어나니
has been granted in marriage by the Empress Dowager
태후의 자애로운 뜻을 받들어
to Young Lord Xiao of Prince Jing'an's Mansion.
특별히 정안왕부 세자와의 혼인을 하사하노니
The wedding will be held on an auspicious day.
길일을 택해 혼례를 올리도록 하라
-Yes, Your Majesty.
- 소신, 명을 받들겠습니다 - 신첩, 명을 받들겠습니다
Congratulations, Your Highness.
경하드립니다, 세자 전하
Thank you for your hard work, Eunuch.
하 내관, 고생이 많으십니다
You flatter me, Crown Princess.
황송하옵니다, 세자빈 마마
The Empress Dowager said
태후마마께서 말씀하시길
that you are one of the family.
세자빈은 한 식구이니
Please rest assured.
걱정 마시라 하셨습니다
May the Empress Dowager enjoy good health.
태후마마께서 강녕하시니
I understand.
원희도 알고 있습니다
Lady Xie will also be part of our family in the future.
훗날 사 씨 동생도 한 식구가 되겠지요
I will take my leave now.
그럼 소인은 이만 물러가겠습니다
You've worked hard, Your Highness.
세자 전하, 수고하셨습니다
Then the details of the wedding...
혼례 준비는
Please don't worry.
염려 마십시오
It is my duty.
제가 마땅히 해야 할 일입니다
Great.
좋소
Wuyi,
둘째야
where are you going?
어디 가느냐?
I heard there's a hot spring in the western suburbs.
서교에 온천이 있다고 들었는데
It's rare for me to return to the capital,
모처럼 경성에 왔으니
so I want to enjoy the hot spring.
가서 즐겨 볼까 합니다
Are you interested too?
형님께서도 흥미가 있으십니까?
Since it's your first meeting with the Crown Princess today,
오늘 처음 세자빈을 만나는 것인데
are you already leaving?
벌써 가려는 것이냐
Crown Princess, could it be
혹시
that you want to come along?
세자빈도 함께 가겠소?
Are your clothes packed?
의복은 다 챙기셨습니까?
Ruisheng has prepared them.
예생이 다 챙겼소
Then,
그럼
farewell, Your Highness.
조심히 가십시오, 전하
[Grand Tutor's Mansion]
[태부부]
Nanxing!
남성
The Young Lady ran away!
아가씨께서 도망치신 거야?
[For Lejun, to be opened personally]
[악군 친전]
Is Granny, who is half-blind, feeling better?
할머니는 몸이 좀 괜찮아지셨나요?
Thank you for your concern, My Lady. She's still in good shape.
아가씨께서 염려해 주신 덕에 아직 정정하십니다
Then I'll leave the trip to Yongzhou in your hands and Granny's.
그럼 이번에 옹주로 가는 길 잘 부탁드릴게요
I thought you were really here for the hot spring.
전하께서 진짜 온천욕 하러 오신 줄 알았습니다
Is everything arranged?
다 준비됐느냐?
Rest assured, Your Highness.
세자 전하, 안심하십시오
Madam Rui has taken the dancers to the hot spring villa.
예씨 부인께서 무희들을 데리고 온천 별장으로 가셨습니다
With all the singing and dancing,
가무가 한창일 테니
even if someone asks,
전하께서 어디 계신지
I guarantee no one will know where you are.
아무도 모를 겁니다
Your Highness,
세자 전하
something is wrong with the two villages near the ferry.
나루터 주변의 두 마을이 좀 이상합니다
What's suspicious?
수상한 점이 있더냐?
Their accents.
말투가 수상합니다
The villagers don't sound like they are from the suburbs.
마을 사람들 말투가 경성 근교 사람 같지 않았습니다
And the fields are abandoned.
게다가 밭은 황폐해졌고
The crops haven't been watered for days.
농작물에도 여러 날 물을 주지 않은 듯 했습니다
More men or women?
사내가 많더냐, 여인이 많더냐
More able-bodied adults, or more elderly people and children?
장정이 많더냐, 노인이 많더냐
More able-bodied men.
장정이 많았습니다
I haven't seen many women.
여자는 거의 보지 못했습니다
That makes sense.
그럼 됐구나
But in this world,
허나 요즘 같은 세상에
how can a village only have strong men?
장정만 있는 마을이 어디 있단 말입니까
Qing Long,
청용아
how is your reading going lately?
요즘 책은 좀 읽고 있느냐?
I haven't read much.
거의 읽지 못했습니다
Do you know what
이화접목
"replacing the old with the new,
암도진창
moving things under cover,
투천환일
and swapping the heavens and the earth" means?
무슨 뜻인지 알겠느냐?
You mean these villagers are all impostors?
이 마을에 있는 모두가 가짜라는 말씀이십니까?
What about the original villagers?
원래 마을의 주민은요?
Were they all killed?
모두 죽임을 당한 것은 아니겠지요
Who would do this?
누가 이런 짓을...
It's Prince Changsha.
장사왕입니다
-He's trying to seize control of the river transport routes. -Prince Changsha...
조운을 장악하기 위해서 말입니다
Then the nearby granaries must be controlled too.
그럼 근처 창고도 이미 넘어갔을 겁니다
Prince Changsha's appetite
장사왕의 욕심은
goes far beyond the ferry and granaries.
나루터와 조운 정도로 간단하지 않아
What he wants is the entire capital.
그자가 원하는 건 경성 전체지
The entire capital?
경성 전체라고요?
If I am not mistaken,
내 짐작이 맞다면
the villages, mountains, forests,
경성 주변의 마을과 산림
ferries, and granaries
나루터와 창고에
are already filled with his troops and assassins.
이미 장사왕의 사병과 결사대가 깔려있을 것이다
He is even faster than I expected.
내 예상보다 더 빠르군
Slow down. The things inside are very expensive.
조심하세요 이 안에 비싼 게 들어있어요
Okay.
알겠습니다
Be careful.
조심하세요
Why does this lady look so familiar?
저 아가씨 어디서 많이 본 것 같은데
Put this one in there.
그건 저 안에 넣으세요
It's the one from the Xie family.
사씨 가문 아가씨가 아닙니까
It's Consort Xie.
측비라고 해야지
Why is she getting on a boat?
배에는 왜 타는 거지?
Isn't she getting married?
곧 혼례 아닙니까?
A hidden dragon lingers in quiet grace,
잠룡은 깊은 곳에서도 빼어난 자태를 감추지 않고
a soaring wild goose echoes in the distance.
기러기는 하늘을 날며 먼 하늘까지 그 소리를 울린다
Above the thin sky…
하늘 높이...
What comes next?
그다음 뭐더라?
Above the thin sky, I feel ashamed like drifting clouds;
하늘 높이 구름을 우러러 부끄럽네
by the riverbank, I stand humbled before the deep abyss.
깊은 연못의 용을 생각해도 부끄럽구나
In pursuing virtue, I lack the wisdom for it.
덕을 이루기에는 재능이 모자라고
As for retreating to farming, I lack the strength for that either.
물러나 농사짓고 살기에도 역부족이로다
Miss, you recited the poem incorrectly.
낭자, 시를 잘못 읊으셨소
This poem is about Xie Lingyun recovering from a long illness,
이 시는 사령운이 오랜 병에서 막 회복하여
climbing a tower and gazing afar, expressing his feelings.
누각에 올라 경치를 보며 느낀 바를 쓴 것이오
It vents his frustration over his political failure.
관직 생활에 대한 실의와 푸념을 담은 것이지요
Since you are not an official,
낭자께선 관직에 계신 것도 아니니
it's inappropriate for you to recite this poem.
이 시를 읊는 건 어울리지 않는듯 하오
You think you know everything.
아는 척 하기는
Such a pretty face,
멀쩡하게 생겨서는
and yet you can't keep your mouth shut.
입만 살았네요
Who are you?
당신 뭐예요?
You don't know me?
나를 모르시오?
You have a lot of nerve.
낯짝 한번 두껍네요
Why should I know you?
내가 당신을 알아야 해요?
So she doesn't know me yet.
아직 나를 모르는구나
May I know your surname, miss?
낭자 성함이 어찌되오?
Where are you going?
어디로 가는 길이오?
None of your business.
무슨 상관이에요?
Such a pretty face,
멀쩡하게 생겨서
and yet you can't keep your mouth shut.
입만 살았소
What did you say?
뭐라고요?
Boatman, who is this man?
사공, 이 자는 누구예요?
Why is he on the boat I chartered?
왜 내 배에 태운 거냐고요
You!
당신
Why did you pull your hand back?
손을 왜 놔요?
Men and women should not have physical contact.
남녀가 유별한 법이오
Then why did you reach out in the first place?
그럼 손을 왜 내밀었어요?
Saving one life is worth more than building a seven-story pagoda.
사람 목숨 하나 구하는 게 칠층탑을 쌓는 것보다 낫다잖소
So what does it mean to only save half and then stop?
그럼 구해주다 마는 건 또 뭔데요?
I realized you weren't going to die anyway.
안 구해줘도 안 죽을 것 같았소
Rules matter more.
법도가 더 중요하니 말이오
Fine.
좋아요
You, I...
당신, 내가...
Boatman, who is this?
사공, 이 자는 누구냐니까요
Why is he on my boat?
왜 내 배에 태웠냐고요
How's today's "fat sheep" doing?
오늘 이 먹잇감은 어떤가?
Very good.
아주 좋네
Which young lady is this,
어느 댁 아가씨길래
traveling alone
이렇게 많은 금은보화를 지니고
with so much gold and silver?
혼자 다니는 거지?
An eloped bride.
혼인 깨고 도망쳤나 보지
The half-blind man said she was going to Yongzhou.
애꾸가 말하기로는 옹주로 간다고 하던데
Once she's on my boat,
내 배에 탔으니
where it goes
이 배가 어디로 갈지는
is not up to her.
내가 결정하는 거지
Boatman!
사공
This is not how you do business.
왜 장사를 이런 식으로 해요?
Is anyone there?
누구 없어요
Where did everyone go?
다들 어디 갔지?
What? It stinks.
뭐야, 악취가 심하네
Boatman.
사공
Tung oil?
오동기름?
Let me go!
이거 놔
Why are there so many women?
웬 여인들이 이렇게 많지?
Wait.
잠깐
You're untying them without even asking?
묻지도 않고 막 풀어주면 어떡하오?
Ask what?
뭘 물어봐요?
This is obviously a suspicious boat.
딱 보니까 수상한데
Could they have tied themselves up?
저 사람들이 제 발로 묶어 달라고 했겠어요?
Who is it?
누구냐
Which blind bastard is this?
어디서 굴러먹다 온 잡놈이냐
Beast!
짐승 같은 놈
I'll blow you up!
터져 죽어라
You!
너
Wait a minute.
잠깐, 잠깐만
How dare you traffic people!
감히 인신매매를 해?
Go with me to see the officials.
가자, 관아로 가
Get up.
일어나
Report to the officials?
관아에 신고한다고?
Which officials?
어느 관아에 말이오?
The Capital Prefect!
경조윤이지요
And who's the complainant?
그럼 고발한 사람은 누구요?
Me.
나요
And who are you?
당신은 누구시오?
Forget it, I'll go find the ferry officials.
됐어요 나루터 관리를 찾아가야겠어요
Where are you going?
어딜 가?
Little lady,
아가씨
curiosity
호기심이 너무 많으면
can get you killed.
제 명에 못 죽는 법이지
I do know a bit of martial arts.
나도 무술 좀 할 줄 알아요
Stay behind me.
내 뒤에 숨어요
Such a pretty face.
예쁘장하게 생겼는데
What a pity.
아깝게 됐군
Where are those martial arts skills of yours?
무술 실력은 어딨소?
I only know a little.
아주 조금 밖에 못 해요
Where is your hidden weapon?
암기는?
Use it.
써 보시오
I'm out. I only had two.
없어요, 두 개뿐이었어요
He...
여협
Heroine, spare my life!
여협, 목숨만 살려 주십시오
Do you surrender?
항복했어요
Spare my life!
살려주십시오
Your Highness,
군주님
Jiayu ran away.
가어가 도망쳤어요
So she actually got away.
결국 도망쳤구나
We should hurry and send someone to find Jiayu.
어서 사람을 보내 가어를 찾아오게 하세요
Jiayu most likely went to Yongzhou
아마 옹주로 갔을 것이다
to find your brother, Prince Qi.
네 오라버니인 기왕 전하를 찾으러 말이야
Why do you want me to bring her back?
너는 왜 내가 그 아이를 찾아오길 바라는 거니?
Don't you want them to be together?
둘이 이어지길 바랐던 거 아니었어?
Of course I hope
저야 당연히
my brother and Jiayu can eventually end up together.
오라버니께서 가어와 맺어지시길 바라죠
But Jiayu grew up in the capital.
하지만 가어는 어릴 때부터 경성에서 자랐고
The farthest she's ever been is the outskirts of the capital.
가장 멀리 가본 곳도 고작 경성 근교예요
If Jiayu goes to Yongzhou alone,
그런 가어가 혼자 옹주에 가면
something will definitely happen to her.
분명 무슨 일이 생길 거예요
Nanxing, come here.
남성, 이리 오너라
Yes, Your Highness.
예, 군주님
I'll do it right away.
제가 바로 처리하겠습니다
I'm a legitimate merchant.
저는 평범한 상인인데
For no reason at all,
아무런 이유도 없이
I was kidnapped and brought here by this demoness.
이 여자 악마한테 여기까지 납치당했습니다
My Lord, you must give me justice.
제 억울함을 풀어 주십시오
What are you looking at?
뭘 봐요?
This boatman traffics people and abducts innocent women.
이 뱃사공은 인신매매에 여성을 겁탈하기까지 했어요
You're the ferry official here.
당신이 이 나루의 관리죠?
Such a heartless thing has happened,
이렇게 천인공노할 일이 벌어졌으니
so you won't be able to escape either.
당신도 책임을 피할 순 없을 거예요
Who are you?
당신은 누구시오?
I am a passenger.
배를 탄 사람이지요
By the way, I also have a few chests.
맞다, 제 짐 상자도
They were also taken by them.
저들이 가로챘으니
You have to get them back for me.
찾아 주셔야겠어요
And you?
자네는
He was fighting with me over the boat.
저랑 배를 타겠다고 싸운 사람이에요
He took so much of my money
제 돈은 있는 대로 다 받아 놓고
and sold the same boat to two people.
이중으로 팔아넘기다니
So corrupt.
날강도 같으니
Who sold it to two people?
누가 이중으로 팔았다는 거야?
I don't even know him!
나는 저 사람을 모른다니까
If you aren't here to fight for the boat,
나랑 배 타겠다고 싸운 거 아니었어요?
then what are you here for?
그럼 뭐 하러 온 건데요?
I...
나는
I came to do business with the boatman.
뱃사공과 거래하러 왔소
The business didn't go through,
거래는 성사되지 않았지만
but I got to watch a good show.
덕분에 재미있는 구경을 했소
You don't need to look at him.
저 사람 볼 거 없어요
Now I've brought the man to you.
제가 이미 사람을 데려왔으니
Report it to the authorities if you have to.
관아에 신고하든 알아서 하세요
Report what?
무슨 신고를 한단 말이오?
You just said
아까 말하길
someone was seized?
누가 겁탈당했다고 했소?
Did someone bully you?
누가 널 괴롭혔느냐?
Don't be afraid.
겁내지 마세요
Just tell us
방금 저자가 무슨 짓을 했는지
what he did to you earlier.
말하기만 하면 돼요
Someone is here to stand up for you now.
이제 네 편이 되어 줄 사람이 있어요
I...
저...
I came of my own free will.
제가 원해서 한 겁니다
My sister and I both signed contracts.
언니랑 저 둘 다 몸 파는 계약서에 서명했습니다
No one forced me.
아무도 강요하지 않았습니다
No one.
아무도요
Then what about her?
그럼 저 여자는?
Her?
저 여자는...
She's the human trafficker.
저 여자가 인신매매범입니다
She has hidden weapons and knows martial arts!
암기도 있고 무공도 할 줄 압니다
Wait, what are you talking about?
아니, 무슨 헛소리예요?
I'm a human trafficker?
내가 인신매매범이라고요?
I just saved...
방금 내가 구해...
You have to testify for me.
나를 위해 증언해 줘야겠어요
I was obviously trying to save her.
나는 분명히 저 여자를 구하려던 거였잖아요
You...
당신들
You're in this together.
한패예요?
Take her down.
잡아라
Wait.
잠깐
Since the trafficker has been caught,
인신매매범도 잡았으니
it's time to talk about our business.
이제 우리 거래를 얘기할 때가 된 듯한데
Okay.
좋소
Let's go.
가자
Let me go.
이거 놔요
Let me go!
이거 놓으라고
Get inside.
들어가
Behave.
얌전히 있어
Run!
도망치시오
A hidden dragon lingers in quiet grace,
잠룡은 깊은 곳에서도 빼어난 자태를 감추지 않고
a soaring wild goose echoes in the distance.
기러기는 하늘을 날며 먼 하늘까지 그 소리를 울린다
Above the thin sky, I feel ashamed like drifting clouds;
하늘 높이 구름을 우러러 부끄럽네
In pursuing virtue, I lack the wisdom for it.
덕을 이루기에는 재능이 모자라고
As for retreating to farming, I lack the strength for that either.
물러나 농사짓고 살기에도 역부족이로다
You're taking credit for my work again.
또 내 공을 가로채네
Cut the crap. How many hidden sentries are left?
헛소리 말고 숨은 보초 몇 명 남았어
There are two left in the northeast.
동북쪽에도 둘 남았어
His Highness is still injured.
세자께선 아직 부상이 있으셔
A fight might not be to our advantage.
싸워봤자 좋을 거 없어
Let's finish this quickly.
속전속결로 하자
If His Highness hadn't insisted on coming himself,
세자께서 직접 오시겠다고만 안 했어도
I would have wiped them all out by now.
진작에 싹 다 처리했을 텐데
Stop talking nonsense.
무슨 말이 그렇게 많아?
Get to work.
빨리 일이나 해
May I know your name, brother?
형씨, 성함이 어떻게 되시오?
My surname is Qing,
청 씨 성에
and my given name is Long.
외자 용입니다
Qing Long.
청용
That's an uncommon name.
흔한 이름은 아니오
Sounds like
듣자 하니
an alias.
가명 같소
Fake or real—
진짜면 어떻고
what does it matter?
가짜면 어떻소
If you're
진짜라면
taking the straight path,
진짜라면 정식으로
there's a price.
처리하는 값이 있고
If you're taking the shadow path,
가짜라면 은밀히 처리해야 하니
there's another price.
또 다른 값이 있는 것이지
Which path are you on, brother?
대체 뭘 옮기려는 것이오?
This item.
이것이오
The tung oil on it
여기에 있는 오동기름은
is used for transporting military equipment.
군수품 운송에 필수적인 물건이지요
I suppose those girls being sold
팔려던 그 아가씨들은
are just a cover for something else.
그저 눈속임일 뿐이고
Your real business is smuggling military equipment.
당신들이 진짜 하고 있던 건 군수품 밀매가 아니오?
Should I just run off on my own…
나 혼자 도망쳤네
Is that really a good idea?
이래도 되나?
He did save me after all.
그래도 날 구해 줬는데
Forget it, forget it.
아냐, 됐어
He probably has a way out anyway.
방법이 있겠지
Where did she go?
어디 갔지?
Not on my side.
이쪽엔 없습니다
Keep searching. Let's go.
계속 찾아봐, 가자
Why
어째서
are they all dead?
다 죽은 거지?
Those people outside aren't real canal workers, are they?
밖에 있던 자들은 진짜 조운 인부가 아니지
Who exactly are you?
대체 누구냐
The real ferry officials and canal workers
진짜 나루터 관리와 조운 인부들은
were killed by you long ago.
진작에 네놈들 손에 죽었겠지
You are Prince Changsha's man.
넌 장사왕의 사람이구나
Were those repeating crossbows that harmed the soldiers of the Beifu Army
우리 북부 병사들을 해친 그 쇠뇌들이
all transported from here to the northern border?
모두 네놈을 통해 북쪽으로 운반된 것이겠지
Could you be...
설마 당신은...
Xiao...
소
Wu
무
yi.
의
I'm here to save you!
내가 구하러 왔어요
Sorry, I missed.
미안, 빗나갔네요
You're just causing trouble.
방해만 되오
You... You know martial arts?
무술을 할 줄 아는 거예요?
Stop pretending.
연기 그만하시오
Still pretending?
아직도
I'm not pretending.
연기 끝났소?
You're not a merchant
당신도 상인이 아니고
and you're not a good person either.
좋은 사람도 아니잖아요
To think I even wanted to save you just now.
당신을 구하려고 했던 내가 바보지
-How dare you... -Get up!
- 사람을 죽... - 일어나시오
I'm telling you,
잘 들어요
I poisoned the crossbow.
이 석궁에 독을 발라 놨어요
I have the antidote.
나한테 해독제가 있으니
Let me go.
날 보내주세요
Get up.
일어나시오
If I wanted you dead,
내가 당신을 죽일 생각이 있었다면
you wouldn't have survived until now.
당신은 진작 죽었을 것이오
Tell me, where are you going?
말해보시오, 어디를 가는 거요?
I'll see you off.
내가 데려다줄테니
Thanks, but no thanks.
고맙지만 사양할게요
I'll go by myself.
혼자 갈 거예요
I'm going
나는
to Yanzhou.
연주에 갈 거예요
For what?
거긴 왜?
I'm going to get married.
시집가거든요
Did you see those boxes I brought?
내가 가져온 궤짝들 봤죠?
Those are my dowry items.
전부 내 혼수품이에요
How did your parents arrange
부모님은 어찌하여 당신을
such a distant marriage for you?
그리 멀리 시집 보내는 것이오?
My parents treat me very badly.
우리 부모님이 얼마나 나를 홀대하는지
They're forcing me to marry some old widower.
웬 늙은 홀아비한테 억지로 시집보내려 하는 거예요
You know what he's like—old, ugly,
그 홀아비가 얼마나 늙고 못생겼는지 알아요?
and never bathes.
씻지도 않고
And all he does every day is kill people.
맨날 사람 죽이는 게 취미래요
There's someone that disgusting?
그런 끔찍한 인간이 다 있나
Of course.
그러니까요
That's why I'm going to Yanzhou to find my cousin.
그래서 연주에 있는 사촌 오라버니를 찾아가려고요
My cousin is handsome and brilliant.
우리 오라버니는 풍채도 좋고 재주도 뛰어나거든요
So,
그럼
you are running away from your marriage.
도망쳐 나온 것이오?
Exactly.
맞아요
If I really married that old widower,
그 홀아비한테 시집갔다간
my whole life would be ruined.
내 인생 망치는 거잖아요
Good.
좋소
Very good.
아주 좋소
Let's go find a boat.
배 찾으러 갑시다
Are you going to kill people again?
또 사람 죽이려고요?
They are not good people anyway.
좋은 사람들도 아니잖소
But those boatmen don't know anything.
하지만 저 조운선 인부들은 아무것도 몰라요
They're just here to help.
그냥 일을 도우러 온 것뿐이라고요
There are no innocent people in this world.
이 세상에 무고한 사람은 없소
I believe that in this world,
난 이 세상에
no one wants to be a bad person.
악인이 되고 싶은 사람은 없다고 믿어요
They were also tricked into coming here.
저들도 속아서 온 거예요
How do we leave without killing them?
죽이지 않고 갈 수가 없소
I have an idea.
나한테 방법이 있어요
Follow me.
따라와요
Wait.
잠깐
Are you new here?
새로 온 놈들이냐
Yes, we are new here.
네, 새로 왔어요
By the way, the ferry official is looking for you.
참, 관리께서 찾으시던데
The ferry official is looking for us? Why?
관리께서 무슨 일로?
I don't know, but it's urgent.
모르겠지만 엄청 급해 보였어요
Go quickly.
얼른 가 보세요
Yes, it's urgent.
급한 일이랍니다
Let's go.
가자
We have to kill them anyway.
어차피 다 죽일 거
I don't know why Young Lord Xiao
세자께선 왜 저런 연극에 어울려 주시는 거지?
is playing along with this scheme.
대체 뭘 어쩌자는 건지
He's probably afraid of scaring Lady Xie.
사 아가씨가 놀랄까 봐 그렇지
Then what should we do?
그럼 우린 어떡해?
Kill them one by one as they come in.
들어오는 사람만 죽여?
How long will that take?
언제까지 기다려
Is Young Lord Xiao on the boat?
세자께선 배에 오르셨어?
He left.
가셨어
Then let's kill them together.
그럼 시작하자
Soldiers of Prince Changsha,
장사왕 사병들아
your leader has been killed by me!
네놈들 두목은 이미 내가 죽였다
Come out.
나와라
Here is a new one for you.
새것으로 하나 드릴게요
Consider it a thank-you gift for saving me just now.
방금 구해 주신 것에 대한 보답이에요
This thing is not durable.
오래 쓰진 못 하겠소
If it were used on the battlefield,
만약 전장에 가지고 나간다면
it would get people killed.
사람 목숨을 잃게 할 것이오
Who said it's for the battlefield?
누가 전장에서 쓴대요?
It's for noble lords to use as decoration during hunting and banquets.
세도가 공자님들이 사냥이나 연회 때 장식용으로 쓰는 거예요
Decoration?
장식용이란 말이오?
Yes.
네
Few young nobles are good at hunting,
공자님들 중에 사냥을 잘하는 분이 많지 않아요
but they want to pretend they are,
하지만 잘하는 척은 해야 하거든요
so they compete to see whose crossbow looks the finest.
그래서 누구의 활과 쇠뇌가 더 멋진지 겨루는 거죠
That's why I chose this kind of wood.
그래서 제가 이런 목재를 고른 거고요
If it were to be used on the battlefield,
전장에서 쓰려면
it would require poplar wood
버드나무를 써야 하고
and be reinforced with dark iron and ox horn.
현철과 쇠뿔도 더해야 해요
It's a lethal weapon on the battlefield,
전장에서 사람을 죽이는 무기가
but in the capital, it's just for show?
경성에서는 그저 뽐내기 위해 쓰인다니
That's what the buyer asked for.
구매자의 요구 사항이에요
What could I do?
내가 무슨 수가 있겠어요?
Do you still want it or not?
필요해요, 안 필요해요?
If not, give it back to me.
필요 없으면 돌려줘요
Good thing it's not broken.
다행이다, 안 망가졌네
It's a gift for your cousin?
사촌 오라버니한테 줄 선물이오?
Don't touch it.
만지지 마세요
Have you even met the man
당신 부모님께서 찾아 주신 그 서방님을
your parents picked for you?
만나 보긴 했소?
He's old, ugly, and a murderer.
늙고 못생긴 데다 사람까지 죽인다잖아요
I wouldn't want to see him.
만나고 싶지 않아요
Rumors might not be true.
소문은 믿을 게 못 되오
I'm not stupid.
나 바보 아니거든요
You're not?
바보가 아니라고?
I saw him kill many people with my own eyes,
난 그 사람이 수많은 사람을 죽이는 걸 똑똑히 봤어요
just...
마치
Just like you did earlier.
방금 전의 당신처럼 말이에요
I did that to save you.
난 당신을 구하려고 그런 거잖소
But if I hadn't stopped you,
하지만 내가 안 막았으면
you would have killed all of them.
그 사람들을 다 죽였겠죠
You know martial arts,
무공을 할 줄 알면
but martial arts should be used to protect the weak,
약자를 지키는 데 써야죠
not to kill people at will.
함부로 사람을 죽이는 게 아니라
I didn't expect someone your age
어린 나이에
to have such insight.
그런 생각을 하다니
Is that why you saved people several times?
그래서 몇 번이나 사람을 구할 수 있었던 것이군
You saved that orphan girl,
그 고아 소녀도 구하고
and even wanted to save me.
심지어 나까지 구하려고
Pity.
안타깝지만
I failed to save one,
한 명은 구하지 못했고
and the other
다른 한 명은
didn't need my help at all.
내 도움이 전혀 필요 없었지요
But she bit the hand that fed her and betrayed you.
그 여인은 은혜를 원수로 갚고 당신을 배신했잖소
She was just trying to survive.
살기 위해서였을 뿐이에요
You don't resent her?
원망하지 않소?
I'm still perfectly alive,
난 이렇게 멀쩡히 살아 있고
while she is already dead.
그 여인은 죽었는데
What is there to resent?
어떻게 원망하겠어요?
You're quite open-minded.
아주 낙천적이오
It's different from what I imagined.
내가 생각했던 거랑은 좀 다르군
What?
뭐가요?
We're here.
다 왔소
We're here?
다 왔다고요?
Is Yanzhou this close?
연주가 이렇게 가까워요?
When did I ever say I was going to Yanzhou?
나는 연주에 간다고 한 적 없는데
I...
내가...
Why am I back in the capital?
어째서 다시 경성으로 돌아온 거죠?
Take her back to the Grand Tutor's Mansion.
태부부로 데려가라
Yes.
예
You know me?
날 알아요?
Who exactly are you?
당신 대체 누구예요?
Lady Xie,
사 낭자
we will see each other again soon.
금방 다시 보게 될 것이오
Xie?
사...
He...
저 사람은...
Who is he?
저 사람이...
Why are you still here?
어째서 아직도 여기 있는 게냐
Didn't I tell you to go to Xiyue Pavilion
내가 서월루로 가라고 하지 않았느냐
and the East Gate to look for her?
동문으로 가서 사람을 찾아라
Hurry, go!
어서, 어서 가
Yes.
예
What's with these people?
이것들이 정말...
Darling,
부인
you're still drinking tea so leisurely.
아직도 한가롭게 차나 마시고 있소?
Yao Yao is missing.
요요가 사라졌는데
Why aren't you anxious at all?
어찌 그리 태평한 거요
When it was time to discipline her,
훈육이 필요할 땐
you spoiled her rotten.
신경도 쓰지 않았으면서
Is it a bit too late
이제 와서 조급해봤자
to be anxious now?
너무 늦은 거 아닐까요?
If Yao Yao really ran away,
요요가 정말 도망친 거라면
then this marriage...
이 혼사는 어쩌고
This is disobeying an imperial edict.
이건 어명을 거역하는 거요
So what?
어명을 거역하면 또 어때요?
This isn't my first time.
저 운소가 어명을 거역한 게 처음은 아닌데요
Marrying you was also disobeying an edict.
당신께 시집온 것도 어명을 거역한 것이었죠
Besides,
게다가
we won't lose her.
애를 잃어버릴 리도 없고요
Have you always had someone following her?
설마 부인이 사람을 붙여 둔 거요?
Madam!
마님, 마님
Young Lady has returned.
아가씨께서 돌아오셨습니다
She's back?
돌아왔다고?
Someone brought her back.
누가 아가씨를 모셔다주셨습니다
That's wonderful.
잘됐구나
Father! Mother!
어머니, 아버지
-Yao Yao! -Let go of me!
- 요요 - 이거 놔요
-Yao Yao. -Letl Xiao Wuyi come to me!
- 소무의한테 오라고 해요
Father, Mother.
아버지, 어머니
Yao Yao, did I hear that right?
요요, 내가 제대로 들은 거냐
Did you mean Young Lord Xiao?
네가 말하는 게 소 세자냐
Yes.
네
Who else could it be but Xiao Wuyi?
그 소무의 말고 또 누가 있겠어요?
I should have recognized that
눈 하나 깜짝 안 하고 사람을 죽일 때
murderous bastard earlier!
진작 알아봤어야 했는데
And he even told me
저한테 뭐라고 했는지 아세요?
that rumors might not be true.
소문은 믿을 게 못 된다나 뭐라나
Hypocrite!
가식적이라고요
How could he pretend for so long?
그렇게 오래 연기하다니
It seems he's even worse than the rumors.
소문보다 더 지독한 인간이었어요
Grand Tutor. Your Highness.
태부 어르신, 군주님
Young Lord Xiao said
세자께서 말씀하시길
the Empress Dowager's bestowed marriage is a state affair.
태후마마께서 하사한 혼인은 국사이니
If Lady Xie continues to act recklessly,
사 낭자의 행동을 계속 방임했다간
it will bring disaster to your entire family.
멸문지화를 당하게 될 것이라 하셨습니다
Please think twice.
부디 태부 어르신과 군주님께서 심사숙고하시길 바랍니다
He dares to threaten my parents?
우리 아버지 어머니까지 협박해요?
You tell him,
가서 전해요
no way!
어림도 없다고
Young Lord Xiao said if Lady Xie wants to escape the marriage,
사 낭자께서 혼인을 피하고 싶으시다면
she needs to practice her martial arts more.
실력을 더 키우셔야 할 거라 하셨습니다
He...
그...
Yao Yao!
요요, 요요
The Prince Changsha's private troops
장사왕의 사병이
secretly controlled Jiankang Ferry
몰래 검강 나루를 장악하고
and smuggled people and goods.
인신매매와 밀거래를 하고 있었고
Later, they were controlled by Prince Jing'an's Mansion's men.
그 후 정안왕부 사람들에게 넘어갔습니다
I have been secretly protecting Young Lady.
제가 줄곧 아가씨를 비밀리에 보호했습니다
Recently, it's rumored in the capital
요즘 소문에 소 세자가
that Young Lord Xiao took beautiful concubines and dancers to his hot spring villa.
소 세자가 미첩과 무희를 데리고 온천 별장으로 갔다던데
He is quite interesting.
이 소 세자 제법 흥미로운 인물이구나
You may leave now.
이만 물러가 보거라
Yes.
예
Darling!
부인, 부인
Who are you talking to?
누구랑 얘기하고 있었소?
No one.
아무도 없었어요
Yao Yao is having a nightmare.
요요가 악몽을 꾸는 것 같소
Come up and see her.
어서 와서 좀 보시오
Come.
여기요
Don't kill!
죽이지 마세요
She always feels restricted at home
요요는 늘 세상이 넓다면서
and thinks the world is vast.
집을 답답해했죠
Little does she know, outside the capital, the people are already suffering.
경성 밖이 이미 쑥대밭이 된 줄은 꿈에도 모르고요
She has a passionate heart,
의협심은 가득하지만
but she can't even protect herself.
자기 몸 하나 지키지 못해요
This trip must have been a huge blow to her.
이번 일로 충격이 꽤 컸을 거예요
No.
아니에요
Young Lord Xiao already knows
소 세자께서 요요가 혼인을
that Yao Yao ran away from the marriage.
피하려 했다는 걸 알게 됐고
And he even had someone bring her back.
직접 사람까지 붙여 돌려보냈으니
This is a warning.
이건 경고요
It seems Yao Yao has to marry him.
아무래도 요요가 꼭 시집을 가야겠소
With military power in hand,
군사권을 가졌으니
even the Emperor and Empress Dowager have to avoid his sharp edge.
천자나 태후께서도 그 기세를 피해야 할 판이오
Wipe it clean.
깨끗이 닦아라
Your Highness,
세자 전하
al the hidden troops at the warehouse and ferry
조운 창고와 나루터에 숨어 있던 사병들을
have been wiped out.
모두 소탕했습니다
From today on, everything is as usual.
오늘부터 예전과 같이
Nothing has changed here.
아무것도 변한 것은 없다
I understand.
알겠습니다
I won't let the Prince Changsha notice.
장사왕께서 눈치채지 못하도록 하겠습니다
From the looks of it,
상황을 보아하니
Lady Xie doesn't seem to be conspiring with the Prince Changsha.
아가씨는 장사왕과 공모한 것 같지 않습니다
It's more like she's being used.
오히려 이용당한 듯합니다
I also don't think she is
제 생각도 그렇습니다
smart enough for that.
그런 머리가 있는 것 같진 않았습니다
No.
아니
I mean Lady Xie is a kindhearted person.
제 말뜻은 아가씨가 선량한 사람이라는 겁니다
In troubled times,
난세에는
even kindhearted people can harm themselves and others.
선량한 사람도 남과 자신을 해치게 되지
How could he be Xiao Wuyi?
어떻게 그 사람이 소무의일 수가 있지?
My Lady, just eat a little.
아가씨, 조금이라도 드세요
You haven't eaten anything today.
오늘 아무것도 못 드셨잖아요
I have no appetite.
입맛 없어
You were unconscious for three days.
사흘이나 혼수 상태셨어요
You are still weak.
몸이 아직 허약하세요
If you don't rest well,
지금 몸조리를 제대로 안 하시면
you'll be the one to suffer later.
나중에 고생하시는 건 아가씨예요
Just let me suffer.
차라리 괴로워 죽는 게 낫지
These are sweet cakes with osmanthus honey.
이건 계화꿀을 넣은 간식이에요
It's Madam Ruan's latest recipe from Miaoshan Bakery.
묘선재 완 아가씨의 최신 조리법이랍니다
That's more like it.
그러셔야죠
Nanxing,
남성
why are you hiding from me?
왜 날 피해?
What's that in your hand?
손에 든 건 뭐고?
This is
이건
a gift from the Heir of Prince Jing'an.
정안왕 세자께서 보내신 예물이에요
Her Highness asked me to bring it to you.
군주께서 아가씨께 가져다주라 하셨고요
What good things could he possibly give me?
나한테 좋은 걸 주겠어?
Xiao Wuyi!
소무의